你我一定都有过这样的经历: 骑上我心爱的小摩托
We've all been there: you're in your 2006 Honda Civic at an altitude of 60,000 feet,
下班途中在六万英尺以2000公里每小时的速度巡航
cruising along at 1,200 miles per hour on your way home from work.
但突然间 GPS不能用了 自己找不到回家的路了
But all of a sudden, your GPS shuts down, and now you have no idea how to get home.
听起来像是技术限制?
At first this sounds like it's probably a technical limit, right?
比如装在卫星上拿望远镜的猴子们没法跟住你们的速度或高度了
The chimpanzees that they put in the satellites to watch your car with high-powered telescopes
just can't keep up past a certain speed or at a certain altitude.
其实GPS理论上可以在2000公里每小时 或六万英尺以上运行
But that's not quite right—your GPS would theoretically work just fine at 1,200 mph or at 60,000 feet.
实际原因更加奇怪一点 GPS设备制造商会刻意增加这个几乎达不到的限制
The actual answer is much weirder—your GPS manufacturer set those seemingly impossible limits on purpose
为了避免潜在的核战争
because they wanted to stop you from starting a thermonuclear war… technically.
听我慢慢道来
Let me explain.
全球定位系统 GPS 这项服务并不是老天爷白给我们的
The Global Positioning System, as a service, isn't just some free utility that was handed down to us by God.
而是来自于一个比老天爷管的还要宽的机构 美国国防部
It was actually created by the only force more powerful than God: the US Department of Defense.
在七十年代早期 美国在追踪自家核潜艇方面遇到了一点困难
You see, in the early 1970s, the US was having a little trouble keeping track of all of its nuclear submarines,
毕竟不能让这玩意随便乱跑
which, y'know, are not the kind of thing you want to lose track of.
当时潜艇用的一款称为"Transit"的卫星定位系统
At the time, these submarines were being tracked with a satellite navigation system called "Transit",
运行起来和GPS很像
which worked a whole lot like GPS—
和两个以上的卫星测量距离来大致给潜艇定位
a submarine could calculate its approximate location on Earth
by measuring its distance from two or more Transit satellites.
但这个系统缺点在于 天上没那么多卫星
But this system had a bit of a problem: there just weren't enough satellites to go around.
这套系统有五颗卫星服务全球
At any given time, the system would use five satellites to cover the entire Earth,
所以绝大多数时间 潜艇可能只能看到其中一个卫星
and that meant that most of the time, a submarine would only have line-of-sight to one of them.
只用一颗卫星理论上还是可以确定大致位置的
It was still technically possible to calculate a rough location with the measurements from one satellite,
但这涉及到一大堆复杂的物理和数学的东西
but that involved a whole bunch of convoluted physics and math stuff
我就不解释了
that I don't really have time to explain,
我只放一秒钟维基百科的截图
so I'm just gonna put up a screenshot of a Wikipedia article here for exactly one second
好奇的同学可以暂停看一看
and you can go ahead and pause the video if you're into that kinda stuff.
嫌太长不爱看的朋友们 直说结果的话
Now for all the people who didn't pause the video because they're cool and hate science,
这套系统技术上能用 但不完全能用
the main takeaway was that this system technically worked but… not very well.
美军需要为他们的潜艇搞一套更可靠的系统
The US military needed something more reliable for their submarines,
于是就有了我们今天的全球卫星定位系统 GPS
so they rolled out the system we use today: Navstar GPS.
卫星数量更多 设备更精确
There were more satellites, with more accurate equipment,
现代GPS接收机 即使在最偏远的地方也总能同时收到至少四颗卫星的信号
and a modern GPS receiver almost always has line-of-sight
to at least four satellites on even the most remote locations  on Earth.
Yes, even in Ohio.
可虽然国防部为GPS系统豪掷数十亿美元
But here's the thing: when the Department of Defense spent billions of dollars developing GPS,
但它并不是为全球老百姓服务 提升大家生活质量的
it wasn't meant to be a public worldwide utility that made everyone's lives easier and more convenient.
事实上 当时宪法中有一整条规定禁止这样做
In fact, there's a whole section in the constitution prohibiting that.
系统首年投入使用的时候 是完全保密的
For the first year that the system was in use, it was completely classified—
别说让老百姓用了 老百姓甚至不知道它的存在
not only did the public not have access to it, they didn't even know it existed.
原因在于 至少在当时 "知道什么东西在哪里" 是一种很危险的高科技
And that's because, at least at the time, the big technological advancement of
"knowing where stuff is" was really dangerous:
知道潜艇在哪 知道导弹在哪
knowing where your submarines are, knowing where your missiles are,
知道你想炸飞的人在哪 这些都是……你想炸飞那个人的原因
and knowing where the people you want to blow up are are all important ingredients in… blowing people up.
没有其他国家能用到全球定位技术
No other country had access to this kind of global positioning technology,
美国也不想这么早掏裤裆
and the US was not eager to give it up.
但快进到1983年9月
But, fast forward to September of 1983—
大韩航空007号班机 从安克雷奇飞首尔 误入苏联领空
this flight, Korean Air 007, accidentally drifted into Soviet airspace on its way from Anchorage to Seoul,
飞机被击落 全员遇难
got shot down, and everyone on board was killed.
显然 如果美国政府将GPS开放给平民与私人飞机 这起事故就完全可以避免
Now, it was pretty obvious that this incident could have been avoided entirely
if the US government had made GPS accessible to civilians and private airlines.
当时的总统罗纳德·里根 肯定内心有点矛盾
The president at the time, Ronald Reagan, was probably a little conflicted—
一方面滥杀无辜正是他津津乐道的英雄史
on one hand, killing innocent people was his favorite pastime,
但另一方面 他还得应付之后的选举
but on the other hand, he was almost up for reelection.
在1983年开放GPS的使用不会像它刚推出时那样成为一个大的国家安全问题
Making GPS public in 1983
wouldn't be as big of a national security issue as it was when it was first rolled out;
苏联已经在前一年推出了他们自己的GPS系统 格洛纳斯
the Soviet Union had already launched their own GPS system, ГЛОНАСС, the year before,
因此 他们用不用美版GPS已经不重要了
so it didn't really matter if they got their hands on Navstar.
于是 大韩航空空难两周后 里根开放了平民对于GPS的使用
So, two weeks after the Korean Air incident, Reagan opened GPS to the public,
但这也有一些安全方面的注意事项
but this came with a couple of security caveats.
首先 信号是被加扰的
The first was that the signal would be partially scrambled,
所以精确度只有一百米
making it only accurate within about 300 feet or 100 meters.
所以如果有人想轰炸白宫 那么很遗憾 你会打偏
That way, if someone was going to nuke the White House, they might miss by a little bit.
信号加扰在克林顿时期 2000年解除
This restriction was later overturned by Bill Clinton in 2000,
因为他想让年轻人感觉他好牛逼啊
because he wanted young people to think he was cool.
另外一个安全事项是由商务部制定的 就是今天说的这个
Now, the other main caveat was put in place by the Department of Commerce, and it was this.
简言之 所有便携GPS接收机(即可以销售出口美国的)
Basically, any GPS receiver that was exportable—meaning that it could be sold outside the US—
需要加入高度与速度限制 防止设备安装于弹道导弹上
would need to put height and speed limits in place that would shut it down
if it were attached to a ballistic missile.
从那时起 这些限制就被硬编码到几乎所有的GPS中
These limits have been hard-coded into pretty much every GPS ever since;
有些是在超过2000公里每小时或一万八千米高度后关闭接收机
some shut down at 1,200 miles or 2,000 kilometer per hour or above 60,000 feet or 18,000 meters,
有些是两者都满足后才会关闭
and some shut down only when both limits are reached…
虽然法规上写的是"或"的关系 但也无所谓了
even though that's technically not how the law is written, but whatever.
问题是 这个限制会影响到谁?
The big question is… do these limits actually affect anyone?
简单来讲 几乎谁也影响不到 所以这些限制还在
And the short answer is not really—that's kind of why they're still in place;
而正因为几乎谁也影响不到 所以也没什么理由移除它
they don't bother anyone, and there isn't really any point in getting rid of them.
但受影响的人还是有的 比如极个别一些组织
But the long answer is yes, they affect a very specific group of nerds
可能会发送高空探空气球 了解冷冻的大蒜面包什么味之类的
who like to send balloons to high altitude so that they can learn what cold garlic bread tastes like.
但在那帮人鼓起勇气给商务部写信之前
But until those nerds work up the confidence to write a letter to the Department of Commerce,
咱们还是把车速保持在2000公里每小时以下吧
you'll have to keep your car under 1,200 miles per hour.
后面是恰饭
So, okay, your phone can't track your location at 60,000 feet.
But you know what it can do?
It can make you smarter—that is, with the help of our sponsor, Brilliant.
Brilliant is an amazing way of keeping your brain engaged every single day without any hassle.
They have fun, intuitive, interactive lessons on almost any STEM subject you can think of.
Want to know more about the satellites we talked about today?
Try their course on gravitational physics.
Wondering what the deal is with your fingerprints?
You'll learn about that in their course on computational biology.
Your girlfriend keeps cheating on you?
Brilliant can teach you the key to truth-seeking in their course on logic with fun puzzles like this one,
where you have to sit robots on an airplane in a particular order to stop them from killing each other!
With Brilliant, you can be a lifelong learner.
You'll be absorbing complex topics quickly and easily, squeezing in daily lessons during commercials or on your walk to work.
It's a great way to kill some of that spare time, and turn it into something productive.
Best of all, to get started for free, visit brilliant.org/hai or click the button on-screen,
and the first 200 of you will get 20% off Brilliant's annual premium subscription.